Aaron Benesch Papers
Aaron Benesch Papers
1889-1966
1945-1959
Benesch, Aaron G.
0.75 linear ft.
American journalist. Collection includes correspondence, memorabilia, clippings, writings.
2746141
Biographical History
Aaron G. Benesch (1893-1966) was an American journalist in St. Louis and Washington, DC. for more than fifty years. Beginning as copy-boy on the St. Louis Star, he eventually became City Editor of the St. Louis Star-Times, a post he held for 17 years (1934-1951). He was associate editor of the Newhouse National News Service, head of the St. Louis Globe-Democrat's Washington Bureau (1951-1953) and later managing editor of the paper (1953-1957).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Aaron Benesch Papers consists of biographical material, correspondence, memorabilia and writings by Benesch and others.
Biographical material contains a biographical sketch (or possible a letter of recommendation), several clippings about Benesch, and a compilation of statements made about him by others, after his death.
Correspondence consists primarily of congratulatory letters on Benesch's various appointments, including managing editor of the Globe-Democrat and head of the Washington Bureau for Newhouse News. Notable correspondents include J. Edgar Hoover and Dwight D. Eisenhower.
Memorabilia includes an issue of the St. Louis Globe-Democrat from September of 1889 and a number of scrapbooks. Two scrapbooks contain clippings of Benesch's columns; the other two include photographs, letters, clippings and other items.
Writings contains clippings of Benesch's column "By the Mississippi" as well as notes on conversations, remarks prepared for Senator Addabo, and a speech given at a City Editors seminar.
Writings by others consists of a few items about journalism and newspapers.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by name or topic.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Benesch, Aaron G.; St. Louis globe-democrat (Saint Louis, Mo.: 1875); St. Louis star-times.; Journalism -- United States.; Journalists -- United States.; Newspapers -- Missouri -- St. Louis.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Unspecified, 1967.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical sketch, author unknown (Box 1)
  - Clippings about, 1946; 1951-1952,; 1958 (Box 1)
  - Statements on his death, 1966 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - A (Box 1)
  - Bond, Dorothy
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Novelty trophy given to Benesch (Oversize 2)
  - B-D (Box 1)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1956; 1959; includes letters and clippings from other newspapers about polls regarding Eisenhower's popularity (Box 1)
  - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1958-1959; 1961 (Box 1)
  - H-J (Box 1)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1961; press invitation to inauguration; nothing from Kennedy personally (Box 1)
  - K-P (Box 1)
  - St. Louis Globe-Democrat
    - Congratulatory, on appointment as managing editor, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Editorial correspondence, 1951-1957 (Box 1)
  - St. Louis Star-Times
    - Correspondence, 1944-1947 (Box 1)
    - Final issue, 15 Jun 1951 (Oversize 1)
  - S-W (Box 1)
  - Unidentified (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Nameplate from desk (Oversize 2)
  - Photograph, Democratic National Convention, 21 Jul 1952; has creases/cracks from rolling/folding (Oversize 1)
  - St. Louis Globe-Democrat, Sep 1889; only upper half of pages, lower half missing (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Clippings, 1952-1957; most are Benesch's columns from the St. Louis Globe Democrat (Oversize 1)
    - Clippings, 1957-1966; most are Benesch's columns from various papers; the last few pages include clippings of his obituary from various publications (Oversize 1)
    - "Aaron Benesch retires", 1 Jan 1966; clippings, photographs, letters, telegrams, etc. (Oversize 1)
    - "Aaron G. Benesch, Fifty plus years in the field of journalism", 1927-1954; clippings, photographs (Oversize 1)
- Writings
  - "By the Mississippi" columns, 1951 (Oversize 2)
  - Notes, Eisenhower interview (Box 1)
  - Notes, Jim Connor (Box 1)
  - Notes, TedSchafer (Box 1)
  - Remarks, written for Senator Joseph P. Addabo, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Speech, City Editors seminar, Columbia University, Dec 1946 (Box 1)
  - Fragments (Box 1)
- Writings by others (Box 1)
  - "Readability and the individual newspaper," VIncent Jones, 1950 (Box 1)
  - "Reading and newspapers," Nieman Alumni Council, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Tripp questionnaire, "...opinions of 1850 to 1875 which inspired our recent symposium..." (Box 1)